A Guide to the Andy McCutcheon Papers, 1936-2012
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Andy McCutcheon Papers, 1936-2012
The Library of Virginia
50952
2.5 cubic feet (6 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charlotte McCutcheon, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Andrew Haliday McCutcheon, Jr., was born in Webster Springs, West Virginia on 12 May 1927. He was the son of Andrew Haliday McCutcheon, Sr. and Elsie Elizabeth Hamrick. He graduated from Stonewall Jackson High School in Charleston, and then attended the University of Tennessee on a football scholarship, but left to join the Navy during World War II. Following his military service, he graduated from Washington and Lee University, and then joined the sports staff of the Richmond News Leader in 1949. McCutcheon then served as executive assistant to Reps. J. Vaughan Gary and David E. Satterfield, and then a year as a special assistant in the Office of Economic Opportunity under Sargent Shriver. He was the unsuccessful Democratic nominee for Congress in the Eighth District of Virginia in 1968, and a year later managed the successful campaign of J. Sargeant Reynolds for Lieutenant Governor of Virginia. McCutcheon co-authored a book on Sargeant Reynolds in 1996. He later served as a chairman of the Henrico County Democratic Committee. He also was an executive with Reynolds Metals Company. He was a trustee of St. Matthew's Episcopal Church, and served on the boards of the Library of Virginia Foundation, J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College Foundation, and on the Screening Committee of the Virginia Sports Hall of Fame. He married Charlotte Andrews in Suffolk, Virginia on 26 January 1952. McCutcheon died in Richmond on 12 February 2012.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1936-2012, of Andy McCutcheon (1927-2012) of Richmond, Virginia, relating to his career as a congressional staffer for Rep. J. Vaughan Gary (1892-1973), his own run for Congress in 1968 against Rep. William L. Scott (1915-1997), and his time as a campaign aide to Lt. Governor J. Sargent Reynolds (1936-1971), his illness and death, and McCutcheon's co-authorship of a biography on Reynolds. The collection also contains information on McCutcheon's participation in high school and collegiate football, his career as a sports writer for the Richmond News Leader, and as an executive with the Reynolds Metals Company. Includes biographical information, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, genealogy and family history materials, memoirs and other writings, obituaries, photographs, press releases, scrapbooks, and speeches.
Contents List
- Biographical Information. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Button - 45th Inauguration, 20 January 1965. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Campaign for Congress, 1968. (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
- Catechism on the Morning and Evening Service of the Book of Common Prayer by Phebe Hagner, 1873. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Certificates. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Clippings. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- College Transcripts. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Deeds. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Deekens, William Carter - Eulogy. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Fall Guys: In the Autumns of Their Discontent" (Draft) by Andy McCutcheon. (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Funeral and Obituaries. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Gary, J. Vaughan. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Genealogy/Family History. (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
- Gleason's Captions. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Ink Stamps. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- International Hod Carriers' Building and Common Laborers' Union of America. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Invitations. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Lady Bird Special" Train Tour, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Laughter, Tears, Tales, and Tributes" by Andy McCutcheon. (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Library of Virginia. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Library Speeches. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- McDowell, Charles. (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
- McDowell, Charles - Memorial Service (DVD), 13 November 2010. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Memoirs. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Memorandum Book. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Military Service. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Navy Patches. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Omicron Delta Kappa. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photographs. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Plaque Labels. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- "Political Dispatches From Heaven". (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Reynolds, J. Sargent. (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Reynolds, J. Sargent. (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
- J. Sargent Reynolds Memorial Room, J. Sargent Reynolds Community College - Dedication Program, 28 June 1998. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Sarge Reynolds: A Documentary, Commonwealth Public Broadcasting (DVD), 2006. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- Reynolds Metals Company. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Reynolds Metals - History. (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
- Ribbon - Inaugural Ball, 20 January 1965. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
- "Rose Bowl Bound" by Andy McCutcheon. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook - Editorial Comments on J. Sargent Reynolds Illness. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Seibel, Fred O. - Original Cartoon, 5 May 1959. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Shriver, R. Sargent - Speech to Young Democrats of Virginia, 30 March 1974. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Sigma Chi, Washington and Lee - Photograph, 1947. (Box 6, Folder n/a)
- Frank P. Soden Roast. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Songs/Poetry. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Speech - Bristol (VA) Manufacturers, 15 December 1977. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Speech - "Government: Friend or Foe?". (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Speech - Institute of Property Taxation, Houston, TX, 9 December 1977. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Speech - Mt. Vernon Democratic Women's Club, 16 March 1977. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Speech - Virginia Association of Professions. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Speech - Virginia Political History Project UVA, 22 July 2005. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Speech - Virginia Public Relations Conference, Virginia Beach, June 1970. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Sports Columns. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Stonewall Jackson High School (Charleston, WV). (Box 4, Folder 13)
- "Third and Long: A One-Act Play" by Andy McCutcheon. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Twin Maples. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- USS George Washington. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Washington and Lee. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- West Virginia Centennial Sports Banquet, 1963. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- "Whatever Happened to...." by James W. Baker, 1992. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Wilder, Lawrence Douglas. (Box 4, Folder 20)